时间索引：03:45 /// 什么是小卫星火箭 [以及它们为何会存在]，06:45 /// 太酷而不能不谈的火箭，
10:15 /// 火箭实验室的电子火箭，13:20 /// 维珍轨道的发射器一号，16:30 /// 阿斯特拉的火箭，19:10 /// 萤火虫的阿尔法，
21:10 /// ABL的RS1，22:30 相对论的地球人-1，24:30 /// 对比，28:30 /// 总结
- Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
- 嗨 是我 Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
Electronics have gotten smaller and smaller and they continue to do so every day,
电子产品正日渐变得越来越小
which of course has led to smaller and smaller satellites as well.
当然 这样的趋势也产生了越来越小的卫星
时间索引：03:45 /// 什么是小卫星火箭 [以及它们为何会存在]，06:45 /// 太酷而不能不谈的火箭，
10:15 /// 火箭实验室的电子火箭，13:20 /// 维珍轨道的发射器一号，16:30 /// 阿斯特拉的火箭，19:10 /// 萤火虫的阿尔法，
21:10 /// ABL的RS1，22:30 相对论的地球人-1，24:30 /// 对比，28:30 /// 总结
原视频名：Who will be the KING of the Small Sat Launchers!
原作者名：Everyday Astronaut
视频来源：youtu.be/A5Sfw58jApo
原视频发布日期：20210528
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
And with these small satellites has emerged
而随着这些小卫星的出现
a whole flood of companies trying to launch small satellites on a more dedicated rocket.
出现了一大批试图用更专用的火箭发射小卫星的公司
After all, sometimes less is more
毕竟 有时少即是多
because it'd be pretty silly to pay for a rocket that has extra performance that you just don't need.
因为花钱买一枚你不需要的具有额外性能的火箭是非常愚蠢的
Why would you have a semi-truck delivering your pizza when a scooter will suffice?
为什么要让一辆半挂卡车来送你的披萨饼 明明一辆摩托车就够了
So today I wanted to do a comparison and a little overview
因此 今天我想做一个比较和一个小小的概述
of some of these key players in the small sat launch industry.
关于小卫星发射市场的主要参与者
With a handful of new launchers getting hardware out on the launch pad
随着一些新发射器(火箭)把设备运到发射台上
launching and some of them even getting to orbit,
随后进行发射 甚至可能入轨
I think now is a good time to give you a rundown on some of these exciting new rockets.
我觉得现在是一个很好的时机来简单介绍一下这些令人兴奋的新火箭
So we'll do a quick little overview on a rundown of some of the features of Firefly's Alpha,
那么 我们将快速介绍以下公司火箭的特点 如萤火虫航天的阿尔法
Virgin Orbit's LauncherOne, Astra's Rockets,
维珍轨道的发射器一号 阿斯特拉的火箭
Relativity Space's Terran-1 rocket, ABL's RS-1
相对论空间的地球人-1火箭 ABL的RS-1
and of course, the current king of small sat launchers,
当然 还有目前的小卫星火箭之王
Rocket Lab with their electron that has launched 20 times.
火箭实验室 因为他们的电子火箭已经发射了20次
But small sat launchers aren't new.
但是小卫星火箭由来已久
So we're also going to compare them all
因此 我们也将把它们都与
to the OG new space private small sat launcher the Falcon 1
与老牌 新兴私人小卫星火箭猎鹰1号进行比较
to see if the industry is catching up to what SpaceX was doing over 10 years ago.
来看看这个行业是否能赶上SpaceX在10多年前的水平
Okay, let's get started.
好吧 让我们开始吧
- [Mission Control] Three, two, one,
-  [任务控制]三 二 一
and liftoff!
起飞
- [Neil] That's one small step for man.
-  [尼尔]这是对人类的一小步
- [Mission Control] That's Houston contact for the test one.
-  [任务控制]这是休斯敦和一号测试的通信
- This video is brought to you by KiwiCo.
- 这个视频是由KiwiCo赞助的
All right, all right.
好的 好的
Right off the bat, I have to make a confession.
在一开始 我就得承认
This isn't a complete list of small sat launchers currently flying
这份名单并不包含所有现役的小卫星火箭
or trying to fly because that list is this long.
或者是研制中的小卫星火箭 因为它们实在太多了
So we had to make some cuts.
所以我们不得不做一些削减
I decided to make a rule.
我决定制定一个规则
The company has to have either attempted to launch
这个公司必须已经尝试过发射
or at least have hardware out on the launch pad and targeting launching in 2021.
或者至少在发射台上有设备 并且目标是在2021年发射
I also wanted all of these rockets to be clean slate designs
我还希望所有这些火箭都是全新的设计
比如米诺陶系列运载火箭是LGM-118和平保卫者弹道导弹的修改版
not just repurpose hardware like some other launch vehicles.
而不是像其他一些运载火箭那样只是某些设备的改型
But of course, that gets confusing
但是 当然 这变得令人困惑
because some of these launchers
因为这之中的部分火箭
will be launching out of shipping containers off the back of a truck.
将从卡车后面的运输集装箱中进行发射
And it doesn't really matter where their launchpad is
而且并不需要考虑发射台的位置
or like Pegasus, it just gets a little bit confusing.
或者则是像飞马座火箭一样(从空中发射) 这只是变得让人困惑
So I promptly broke our rules and I just had to make some executive decisions.
所以我马上打破了规则 而必须得做出一些行政(粗暴的)决定
So sorry if your favorite launcher wasn't included in this rundown,
如果这个视频中并不包含你最喜欢的火箭 那么很抱歉
but we still figure this was a big and comprehensive enough comparison
但我们仍然认为这是一个足够大且全面的比较
for what might be flying by the end of 2021.
对于那些2021年底可能会飞的火箭而言
We want hardware here folks not drawings, no paper rockets.
老哥 我们要的是设备 不是图纸或者说纸面火箭
And if you were expecting to see some of the private launchers from China on this list,
如果你期望在这个名单上看到一些来自中国的私人火箭
unfortunately, we just really don't have a lot of info on them.
不幸的是 我们真的没有很多关于它们的信息
注意军用是很大的范围，不一定指弹道导弹或者说快递，
个人认为主要还是信息不足，可以讲的东西不多，其他都是次要因素
And most of them are just rebranded military solid rocket boosters.
而且它们中的大多数只是换名的军用固体火箭助推器
So, although some of them are really cool and hold a lot of promise,
因此 尽管它们中的一些真的很酷 而且有很大的前景
they didn't quite it on this list.
但并不在这个名单上
And we also aren't including older systems like the Pegasus.
而且像飞马座这样的老系统我们也不会盘点
Because Pegasus could definitely fit a fair amount of these definitions,
因为飞马座绝对可以符合这些定义中的相当一部分
but it's expensive
但它很昂贵
and it literally has no future in commercial space or really almost no future at all.
而且在商业航天中 它几乎没有前途
It's pretty much done.
它几乎已经没了
时间索引：03:45 /// 什么是小卫星火箭 [以及它们为何会存在]，
06:45 /// 太酷而不能不谈的火箭，10:15 /// 火箭实验室的电子火箭，
13:20 /// 维珍轨道的发射器一号，16:30 /// 阿斯特拉的火箭，
19:10 /// 萤火虫的阿尔法，21:10 /// ABL的RS1，22:30 相对论的地球人-1，
24:30 /// 对比，28:30 /// 总结
So here's timestamps for each section and each rocket and the final big comparison for you guys.
那么 这里是给你们准备的每个部分和每个火箭的时间戳 以及最后大比较
Now, of course, there's links to the timestamps in the description of this video.
那么 当然 在这个视频的描述中 有时间戳的链接
The YouTube play bar is broken up into these sections as well,
油管的播放进度条也根据每个部分进行了分割
and there's an article version of this video up at everydayastronaut.com for easy searching and references.
同时 这段视频的文章版本也放在everydayastronaut.com上面 便于搜索和参考
什么是小卫星火箭
[以及它们为何会存在]
[bright upbeat music]
[明亮欢快的音乐]
So before we get into all of this new hardware
因此 在我们开始讲解这些新设备之前
let's first define what a small sat launcher is and why they exist.
让我们首先定义一下什么是小卫星火箭 以及它们存在的原因
A small sat launcher, or technically a small lift launch vehicle is a class of rocket.
小卫星火箭 严格来说是小型运载火箭 是这样的一类火箭
So it's a rocket that's capable of taking up to 2000 kilograms to lower earth orbit.
能将2000千克以下的载荷送入近地轨道
Anything above 2000 kilograms to LEO is technically a medium lift launch vehicle
严格意义上 任何近地轨道运力超过2000千克的火箭 都是中型运载火箭
质子，一次性猎鹰9号Block 5，宇宙神五552应该算大型(国内)/重型(国外)运载火箭，
联盟，重复使用型猎鹰9号Block 5或者v1.0/v1.1，宇宙神五其他型号应该算中型运载火箭
such as the Soyuz, the Proton, the Atlas V or the Falcon 9.
如联盟 质子 宇宙神五 猎鹰9号
So obviously a small lift launcher isn't as capable as a bigger rocket
所以很明显 小型运载火箭的运力不如大型火箭
but they're not really supposed to be.
但实际上它们本就不是为了这样而设计的
With a large number of lightweight satellites that are being built and developed right now,
由于现在有大量正在建造和开发的轻量级卫星
there's plenty of demand for a rocket launcher that can take them directly to their destination.
对能够直接把它们带到目的地的火箭 产生了大量需求
But you might be quick to think why do these rockets even exist
但是 你可能会很快想到 为什么还要存在这些火箭
when the Falcon 9 is already one of the cheapest $/kg rockets ever made
既然猎鹰9号已经是有史以来最便宜的美元/千克火箭之一了
or will this all even matter when Starship is online?
或者 当星船服役时 这一切还会有意义吗？
Well, first off, just like we mentioned in the intro
嗯 首先 就像我们在介绍中提到的那样
you wouldn't expect a pizza to be delivered by a semi-truck.
你不会想用一辆半挂卡车来送一个披萨饼的
Yes, of course, a semi-truck and carry a lot more.
是的 当然 一辆半挂车可以装载更多的东西
And its dollar per kilogram of cargo is pretty cheap
而且它运输单位质量货物的价格也很便宜
but it's just simply not the best option for all payloads.
但它实在不是所有有效载荷的最佳选择
It's a bit overkill.
这实在是杀鸡用牛刀
And the same thing is true with airplanes.
而飞机的情况也是如此
Cessna's still exist at the same time as jumbo jets.
塞斯纳仍然与巨型喷气机同时存在
And even in the jetliner world,
甚至在喷气式客机领域也是如此
a small regional jet taking a few dozen passengers is a completely different need
一架小型支线飞机运送几十名乘客的需求
than flying 100 of people across the ocean as efficiently as possible.
会与尽可能有效地让100人飞越大洋的需求完全不同
Now there's countless examples of this,
现在有无数个这样的例子
but at the end of the day, if you have a 200 kilogram satellite and you want to fly it to a specific orbit,
但最终 如果你想让200千克的卫星送入一个特定的轨道上
you could either pay, say $50 million-ish for a Falcon 9
你要么支付 5000万美元左右的猎鹰9号的费用
or you could maybe pay about $5 million for a smaller rocket that will do the job, no problem.
或者得支付大约500万美元购买一枚较小的火箭来完成这项工作
Now of course, ride sharing is an emerging option
当然 现在 搭车发射是一种新兴的选择
but you're typically at a fairly limited launch cadence and destination.
但通常 发射周期和目标轨道会受到限制
So sure, sometimes hopping on a bus in a big city
那么没错 有时在大城市跳上一辆公共汽车
and getting off a few blocks from your destination is just fine.
并在离目的地几个街区的地方下车是没问题的
But other times you just want an Uber to take right to your front door.
但在其他时候 你只是想让Uber(专车)直接送到你家前门口
Besides that developing a massive rocket requires a lot more capital
此外 开发一枚大型火箭需要更多的资金
and it carries with it a ton more risk.
而且它的风险也大得多
We're talking about development and investments in the billions for rockets
我们谈论的是开发和投资数十亿的火箭
like the Falcon Heavy, Starship, New Glenn or Vulcan.
像猎鹰重型火箭 星船 新格伦或火神
So brand new rocket company would probably be pretty silly
因此 全新的火箭公司这样想可能是非常愚蠢的
蓝色起源：感觉有被冒犯到
to think they could just come out of the blue and sink billions of dollars into a huge rocket
也就是突然出现 并为一枚巨大的火箭投入数十亿美元的资金
instead of starting with a smaller, less risky program
而不是从一个规模和风险较小的项目开始
that may only cost a few million dollars to get off the ground, literally.
而这个项目可能真的只需要花费几百万美元就能启动
Okay, so small lift launchers. Cool.
好吧 那么小型运载火箭是合理的
Now, let's talk about a few of these and what makes them stand out in a sea of potential space Ubers.
现在 让我们谈谈其中的几个 以及是什么让它们在潜在的太空专车海洋中脱颖而出
We're just going to briefly describe these rockets
我们只是要简要介绍一下这些火箭
and then do a side-by-side comparison of their exact capabilities at the end.
接着在最后对它们的确切能力做一个并排的比较
太酷而不能不谈的火箭
Orbex /// Skyrora /// 火箭
[bright upbeat music]
[明亮欢快的音乐]
Now, before we get into the official ones that we chose,
现在 在我们开始正片的内容之前
I did have to touch on a few that are just too cool to not talk about
我必须谈谈一些因为太酷而不能不谈的东西
but they're probably not going to be flying in 2021.
但它们可能不会在2021年飞行
And I really hope we see them fly 'cause some of these systems are just awesome.
而我真的希望能看到这些火箭飞行 因为其中的一些系统实在是太棒了
Orbex is working on a very unique rocket that we don't know a ton about called Prime.
Orbex正在研制一种非常独特的火箭 我们对其了解不多 叫做Prime
The things that make this rocket super unique
这枚火箭超级独特的地方
besides launching from the UK
除了从英国发射之外
is the fact that it has coaxial tanks.
则是它使用了同轴储箱
This means the fuel tanks housing liquid propane are actually inside the liquid oxygen tanks.
这意味着容纳液态丙烷的燃料储罐实际上位于液氧储罐内
They both run the length of the stage vertically like a tube inside of a tube.
就像管子里的管子一样 垂直地贯穿整个分级
The use of propane is key
关键是丙烷的使用
because when it's surrounded by cryogenic liquid oxygen, it doesn't freeze solid.
因为其被低温液氧包围时 不会凝固
It stays a liquid.
会保持液态
And we don't know a ton about the engines themselves
而且我们对发动机本身并不了解
or even what the first stage will look like
甚至一级也不清楚
other than they plan on it being reusable.
只知道他们计划将一级重复使用
But keep your eye out for Orbex.
但Orbex值得留意
Another one that's gonna be flying from the UK is Skyrora with their Skyrora XL launch vehicle.
另一个将从英国起飞的是Skyrora的Skyrora XL运载火箭
This rocket will be pretty cool because of the same reason.
出于同样的原因 这枚火箭也会是相当酷的
It also uses coaxial tanks.
它也使用同轴储罐
I don't know where you guys across the pond are doing over there
我不知道你们这些大西洋对面的人都在做啥
and what your love with coaxial tanks are,
以及你们到底有多喜欢同轴储罐
but I love it.
但我喜欢它
Skyrora XL will run on high test peroxide or HTP for the oxidizer
Skyrora XL将使用高浓度过氧化氢 简称HTP作为氧化剂
and RP-1 for the fuel.
使用RP-1作为燃料
It'll have nine Sky Force engines on its first stage
其一级会配备9台天力发动机
kick stage意为用来踢一脚的分级，为了方便字幕，统一简写为末级，或者额外的末级/三级等
and a single vacuum Sky Force engine on the second stage and a pressure fed, kick stage.
二级使用一台真空天力发动机 以及一个挤压循环的末级(三级)
Their engines are a unique closed-ish cycle.
他们的发动机使用一种独特的闭式循环
There'll be using basically a monoprop to spin the pumps.
基本上会使用一台涡轮来旋转燃料泵
So decomposed peroxide, much like the RD-107 and RD-108 on the Soyuz.
那么分解的过氧化物 很像联盟火箭上的RD-107和RD-108
But instead of dumping it overboard,
但分解后的产物不会排到发动机外面
they're gonna be piping that right back into the main chamber.
而是使用管道再将其送回主燃烧室
大概是因为过氧化氢分解不算燃烧，所以不算分级燃烧
So it's technically closed cycle but not staged combustion cycle.
因此 严格意义上 它是闭式循环 但不是分级燃烧循环
Something cool I've never seen that done before so I thought that was pretty awesome.
一些很酷的事情 我以前从未见过这样做 所以我认为那是非常棒的
But we don't really know anything else about the Skyrora XL,
但我们对Skyrora XL还不太了解
so we'll be watching out for them closely too.
所以我们也会密切关注他们的情况
And lastly, we have to talk about the rocket launching launch company, Launcher.
最后 我们必须谈谈火箭发射的发射公司 火箭
No, wait, rocket launching company, Launcher.
不 等等 火箭发射公司 火箭
There we go.
这就对了
They're working on a rocket called Rocket-1.
他们正在研制一种叫做火箭-1的火箭
So yes, Rocket-1 is going to be launched by Launcher.
所以 是的 火箭-1将由火箭公司发射
This will never get confusing.
这真是不会让人困惑的名字呢
Besides having a handful of exciting contracts and very healthy funding,
除了有少数令人振奋的合同和非常多的资金外
the most exciting thing to me is they're pursuing a closed cycle oxygen rich Kerolox engine
对我来说 最令人兴奋的是他们正在研制一种富氧闭循环液氧煤油发动机
called, wait for it, Engine 2 or just E-2.
叫做 等下哈 发动机2或者简称E-2
This thing is incredible.
这个东西是不可思议的
It can hit 365 seconds of specific impulse in a vacuum, which is amazing.
它可以在真空中达到惊人的365秒的比冲
It's 3D printed and the main chamber and the nozzle are copper alloy
它是3D打印的 而主燃烧室和喷嘴是铜合金的
which just simply looks awesome.
这简直棒极了
Now, they don't have a launch pad picked out yet
现在 他们还没有选好发射台
and we don't really know when we can expect to see them fly
而且我们真的不知道什么时候才能看到他们的飞行
but they have a lot of potential and I just really want to see that E-2 engine fly.
但这有很大的潜力 而且我真的只是想看到E-2发动机的飞行
That thing looks amazing.
那东西看起来很神奇
Okay, so those are some of the vehicles I just had to mention quickly
好的 所以这些是我不得不快速提及的一些火箭
that didn't make the cut for this video
同时也没能出现在接下来的部分中
but hopefully they continue to mature and get out to the launch pad soon
但希望它们能继续成长 并尽快运抵发射台(准备发射)
because I wanna see all of them fly.
因为我想看到它们全部都飞起来
But for now it's on to our main features.
但现在 进入正片
火箭实验室 /// 电子火箭
[bright upbeat music]
[明亮欢快的音乐]
Let's start off with a familiar launch vehicle.
让我们从一枚熟悉的运载火箭开始
Rocket Lab's Electron rocket.
火箭实验室的电子火箭
The Electron is one of the only small lift launchers actively flying to date
电子火箭是迄今为止(为数不多的几种)现役的小型运载火箭之一
with their first launch attempt in 2017,
他们在2017年进行了第一次发射尝试
which was going very smoothly until a ground tracking station lost track of the rocket
一开始非常顺利 直到一个地面跟踪站失去了对火箭的跟踪
and the mission had to be terminated.
而任务不得不终止
But they ended up successfully reaching orbit on their second attempt, less than a year later
但他们最终在不到一年后的第二次尝试中成功进入轨道
which proved the rockets flight worthiness.
这证明了火箭的飞行价值
The Electron has a few features that are super unique and it even sports a few rocketry first.
电子火箭有几个特点非常独特 甚至还首次采用了一些火箭技术
The body is entirely made out of carbon composites with no separate liner or anything.
箭体完全由一整块碳纤维复合材料制成
All carbon fiber baby.
兄啊 这可是完全的碳纤维
This makes it very lightweight and very strong.
这使得它非常轻 而且非常坚固
It also uses electric pump fed engines called the Rutherford.
它还使用名为卢瑟福的电泵发动机
Electric pump fed is a simple design that uses powerful motors to spin the pumps
电泵是一种简单的设计 其使用强大的电机来旋转(推进剂)泵
that pulls the propellant from the tanks
这样能把推进剂从储罐中抽取出来
and forces them into the combustion chamber at high pressures.
并迫使其在高压下进入燃烧室
The Rutherfords are also 3D printed
卢瑟福发动机也是3D打印的
which for a rocket engine, this size makes a ton of sense.
对于这样尺寸的发动机来说 是明智的
There are nine sea level Rutherford's on the first stage
第一级上有9台海平面的卢瑟福发动机
and a single vacuum optimized Rutherford on the upper stage
而二级带有一台真空优化的卢瑟福发动机
which also runs on RP-1 and liquid oxygen otherwise known as Kerolox.
其也使用RP-1和液氧 也称为液氧煤油
The Electron launches from either LC-1A or soon LC-1B on the Mahia Peninsula in New Zealand.
电子火箭从新西兰马希亚半岛上的LC-1A 或者很快会是LC-1B发射
MARS = Mid-Atlantic Regional Spaceport，中大西洋区太空空港
And then there's also MARS Pad 0C at Wallops, Virginia
然后还有位于弗吉尼亚州沃洛普斯的MARS Pad 0C
that Rocket Lab actually calls LC-2.
火箭实验室实际上称之为LC-2
So we haven't seen them fly from there yet but hopefully it's gonna fly there really soon.
所以我们还没有看到他们从那里飞行 但希望很快就会做到
Another fun note about Rocket Lab is that
关于火箭实验室的另一件有趣的事是
there are technically an American aerospace company
严格来说 他们是一家美国航天公司
but founded in New Zealand with a wholly owned New Zealand subsidiary
但成立于新西兰 拥有一个全资的新西兰子公司
截至2021.06.02应该还没有完成上市流程，但应该可以交易SPAC公司的股票
who is now actually publicly traded on the New York stock exchange.
他们现在实际上在纽约证券交易所公开交易
And full disclosure, I am a proud shareholder.
而且透露一下 我也是一个自豪的股东
By being a US company with US headquarters, they found a great way to make it
一家拥有美国总部的美国公司
so they could fly NASA and US military payloads really easily.
可以非常容易地发射美国国家航空航天局(NASA)和美军的有效载荷
And they could also develop the avionics and engines in the US.
而且还可以在美国开发航电设备和发动机
But one of the most exciting things about the Electron is Rocket Lab is actively pursuing reusing it.
但是 关于电子火箭最令人兴奋的事情之一是 其正积极准备进行重复使用
youtu.be/ZIaDWCK2Bmk
Now, I've done a video on this topic
那么 我已经做了一个关于这个主题的视频
why their plans to use just a parachute and a helicopter should work
为什么他们只使用降落伞和直升机的计划会成功？
and why SpaceX or other companies don't do something more similar to this.
以及为什么SpaceX或其他公司不做与此类似的事情
As of the making of this video they've successfully recovered two electrons
截至本视频制作时 他们已经成功地回收了两枚电子火箭
and reuse some of the parts of the first recovered rocket.
并重新使用第一枚回收的火箭的一些部件
And I have no doubt that we'll see a fully recovered and reused Electron in the near future.
而且我相信 在不久之后 电子火箭会进行完全的回收和重复使用
One more detail about Rocket Lab's Electron is it has a third stage
关于火箭实验室的电子火箭 还有一个细节是它拥有三级
and that third stage can do a lot
而且这个三级火箭能完成很多工作
including sending payloads to the moon or even to Venus.
其能将有效载荷送往月球甚至金星
They have a basic cold gas kick stage
三级可以选配基本的冷气发动机末级
with a tiny little engine called the Curie engine to circularize their orbits
其使用一个叫做居里发动机的超小发动机来使其轨道圆化
or they have a full-blown Photon spacecraft with a hyper Curie
或者选配使用超居里发动机的完整光子航天器
that can be bipropellant and they can even extend the tanks for maximum performance.
可以使用双组元推进剂 甚至可以延长储罐来获得最大性能
Okay, so that's Rocket Lab.
好了 这就是火箭实验室
维珍轨道 /// 发射器一号
Next...
接下来
[bright upbeat music]
[明亮欢快的音乐]
The next smallest launcher to make it into orbit
下一枚已经入轨的最小的运载火箭
and on our list is Virgin Orbit with their super unique LauncherOne.
同时也在我们的名单上的是维珍轨道超级独特的发射器一号
Now notice this isn't Virgin Galactic,
那么请注意 这不是维珍银河公司
it's their sibling company, Virgin Orbit.
是他们的兄弟公司 维珍轨道公司
Virgin Galactic for now is only suborbital space tourism
维珍银河目前只进行亚轨道太空旅游
using their White Knight Two mothership aircraft and their Spaceship 2 rocket plane.
使用他们的白骑士二号母机和他们的太空船2号火箭飞机
Virgin Orbit is different, although kinda the same.
维珍轨道则与之不同 但其实也有共同点
It's a similar idea by using a 747 as a carrier vehicle
这是一个类似的想法 使用747作为载机
that essentially acts like a portion of the first stage
本质上就像火箭一级的一部分
by getting the rocket high up and into the upper atmosphere,
也就是可以把火箭升入高层大气
and then it also gives it some initial velocity.
同时还能提供一些初速度
Now, the truth of the matter is because of how little velocity is actually put into the rocket itself,
现在 事实是 由于(载机)实际投入到火箭的速度很小
the 747 assist is less of a first stage and more of a flying launchpad.
747载机与其说是一级 不如说是一个飞行的发射台
Now, of course it still has its advantages
那么 当然它仍然有其优势
like being able to fly and launch above or around adverse weather conditions
例如 能够在地面处于恶劣的天气条件时 飞到附近或者高空来发射
or fly to exact inclinations for maximum performance.
或者飞行到特定的倾角(纬度/射向)来发射 以获得最大的性能
It also allows them to utilize a more vacuum optimized engine on the first stage
这还允许他们在一级上使用更加真空优化的发动机
which also increases performance.
这也提高了性能
Someday I'll make a video about air launching and why more companies aren't doing it.
以后 我会做一个关于空中发射 以及为什么更多的公司没有这样做的视频
Because on the surface it makes a ton of sense to give the rocket a little boost
因为从表面上看 给火箭增加一点助推是很有意义的
but there definitely are some reasons why it may not be worth it for most engineers and most systems.
但是 对于大多数工程师和系统来说 肯定有一些原因不值得这样做
Pros and cons my friends.
兄啊 这就是有失必有得
It's all about those fun engineering compromises.
这都是关于那些有趣的工程妥协
But back to the system,
但回到这个系统上
the 747 is a 400 series named Cosmic Girl which was originally in Virgin Airlines fleet.
这是一架名为宇宙女孩 的747-400系列 最初在维珍航空的机队中(服役)
A 747 was chosen for a few really, really good reasons.
选择747有几个非常好的原因
First off, it's readily available.
首先 它是现成的
There's thousands of experienced and trained pilots, engineers, mechanics
有数以千计 训练有素的飞行员 工程师和机械师
and parts readily available.
同时零件都是现成的
But another fun reason is
但另一个有趣的原因是
the 747 was actually designed to hold a fifth engine under its left wing
实际在设计上 747左翼下可以容纳第五台发动机
for transporting engines around the world.
用于在世界各地运输发动机
Now, this pylon had to be modified to handle the weight of the rocket
那么 这个支架必须进行修改 以应对火箭的重量
and to drop the rocket mid air, of course
当然 同时还能在空中投放火箭
but the plane was already designed to handle similar loads from the get-go.
但这架飞机从一开始就被设计成可以应对类似的载荷
So that's very cool.
所以这点就非常好
The rocket itself is a two-stage Kerolox rocket
火箭本身是一个两级的液氧煤油火箭
with a single open cycle engine called Newton 3 on its first stage
其一级上使用一台名为牛顿3号的开式循环发动机
and a single open cycle vacuum optimized engine called the Newton 4 on the second stage.
而在二级上使用一台名为牛顿4号开式循环真空优化发动机
One fun little note is the roll of the rocket is controlled by the exhaust from the gas generator,
一件有趣的小事是 火箭的滚转是由气体发生器的排气控制的
which is always something I thought was a really cool idea
一直以来 这是我认为非常酷的一个想法
after I first learned about it from the RS-68 that's on the Delta IV.
在我第一次从德尔塔四号上的RS-68上面了解到这一点之后
Just like Rocket Lab's launch history,
就像火箭实验室的发射历史
Virgin Orbit followed a similar fate with their first launch, which happened in 2020.
维珍轨道公司在2020年进行的首次发射也有类似的命运
The rocket had a clean drop from the carrier plane
载机将火箭干净利落地投下
but the rocket failed shortly after main engine ignition.
但在火箭主发动机点火后不久 发射就失败了
But they successfully made it into orbit on their second launch attempt in January, 2021.
但他们在2021年1月的第二次发射尝试中成功进入轨道
They're now operational and ready for more commercial launches.
现在已经开始运作 并准备好进行更多的商业发射
阿斯特拉
[bright upbeat music]
[明亮欢快的音乐]
Astra's Rocket is what would happen
阿斯特拉的火箭是这样的
if you combine the old school looks of the Atlas Convair SM-65A rocket
如果你把宇宙神康维尔SM-65A火箭的老式外观
with Rocket Labs Electron kind of
和火箭实验室的电子火箭那种(大小)结合
and then launch it from one of the most gorgeous launch sites in the world in Kodiak, Alaska.
然后从阿拉斯加科迪亚克这个几乎是世界上最漂亮的发射场发射
Astra's rocket used to be called Rocket 3
阿斯特拉的火箭曾经被称为火箭3号
and was following a number scheme of 3.0, 3.1, 3.2 for each launch, et cetera et cetera.
而且每次发射都遵循3.0 3.1 3.2等等的编号方案
But Astra actually told me to just simply call it Astra's rocket
但实际上阿斯特拉跟我说 只需简单地称它为阿斯特拉的火箭
likely because they're still evolving so quickly that that numbering scheme just doesn't really make sense.
可能因为他们仍在快速发展 以至于这种编号方案并不具有真正的意义
高情商：数据是阿斯特拉提供的
低情商(弹幕自由发挥)：_______
So our facts and numbers do reflect what Astra told us
那么(这个视频里的)事实和数字确实反映了阿斯特拉告诉我们的那些
and might not necessarily reflect previous Rocket 3 series.
而不一定反映以前的火箭3系列
Astra was a quite little rocket company who was located in Alameda, California
阿斯特拉是一家挺小的火箭公司 位于加利福尼亚州的阿拉米达
which is just across the bay from San Francisco.
与旧金山隔海相望
They were actually known as the stealth space company for a while, until they started test launches.
他们实际上有一段时间被称为隐形太空公司 直到他们开始测试发射
Astra's launch services are a low cost highly portable solution.
阿斯特拉的发射服务是一种低成本的高度轻便的解决方案
One of the most unique features is
几乎最独特的特点是
their ability to fit inside of a standard shipping container
(火箭)能够装在一个标准的集装箱内
and have all of the launch infrastructure, also be able to be shipped via shipping containers.
同时其他的发射基础设施 也能够通过集装箱进行运输
These containers can then be loaded into a C130
这些集装箱接着可以装入C130运输机
and then taken to launch sites around the world.
然后运往世界各地的发射场
This adds a rapid response capability.
这增加了快速反应的能力
Like the other rockets we've talked about so far in this video,
就像我们前面正片中谈过的火箭一样
it also runs on Kerolox on both stages.
它的两个分级上都是用液氧煤油推进剂
The first stage has five of their Dolphin engines,
一级有五台海豚 发动机
which like the Electron are electric pump-fed and 3D printed.
与电子运载火箭一样 它也是由电泵提供动力 并且是3D打印的
And the upper stage has a single Aether pressure-fed engine.
而上面级有一台挤压循环发动机 名为以太
So far there have been three tests launches
到目前为止 已经有三次测试发射
and they were able to demonstrate orbital capability
并且已经可以验证入轨能力了
but they haven't quite made it to orbit to date.
但到目前为止他们还没有完全进入轨道
Their most recent launch attempt in December, 2020
他们在2020年12月的最近一次的发射尝试中
made it past the Karman line and even to their target orbital altitude of 390 kilometers
成功越过卡门线 甚至到达了他们的目标轨道高度390公里
but failed to reach a stable orbit
但未能达到一个稳定的轨道
when it fell just 500 meters per second short of orbit
距离目标轨道仅差500m/s的速度
due to a bad fuel mixture ratio in the upper stage.
由于上面级的燃料混合比不佳
根据CNBC的报道www.cnbc.com/2021/02/02/rocket-startup-astra-to-go-public-astr-via-spac-at-2point1b-valuation.html，
应该是2021年第二季度准备上市，截至2021.06.02应该还没有完成上市流程，但应该可以交易SPAC公司的股票
The company announced plans to become publicly traded in February of 2021
该公司宣布计划在2021年2月上市
through a special purchase acquisition company or SPAC.
通过一个特殊目的收购公司或者说SPAC
Now, again, full disclosure.
那么 再次透露下
I'm also a proud shareholder 'cause I like rockets.
我也是一个自豪的股东 因为我喜欢火箭
Astra is raring to go with 10 plus customers including Planet and NASA ready to go in the next few years.
阿斯特拉公司有10多个客户 包括行星公司和NASA 准备在未来几年内完成发射
Astra is also exploring other launch sites as part of their spaceport strategy.
阿斯特拉也在探索其他发射场 作为其太空港战略的一部分
They're focusing on a complete turnkey lawn solution.
他们正专注于一个完全的快速响应(随地发射)方案
So call them up and they will launch your payload efficiently and affordably.
那么 给他们打电话 之后就将有效地 经济地发射你的有效载荷
It feels like they're putting a lot of extra effort into the customer facing side,
感觉他们在客户公关方面投入了大量的额外努力
which is probably a good thing now with so many new customers hitting the market.
这可能是一件好事 因为现在有这么多新客户进入市场
萤火虫 /// 阿尔法
[bright upbeat music]
[明亮欢快的音乐]
Firefly's Alpha is a rocket that kind of slipped by me a bit.
萤火虫的阿尔法是一枚差点被我漏掉的火箭
I think it was a bit confusing to me
我认为这对我来说有点困惑
because the original company, Firefly Space Systems went bankrupt.
因为最初的公司 萤火虫空间系统公司破产了
And then it got a whole new round of funding and emerged as Firefly Aerospace.
然后它得到了新一轮的资金 以萤火虫航天的名义出现
And when this switch over happened,
而当这种转换发生时
they dropped their original Firefly Alpha Aerospike powered small lift launcher, which that was cool.
他们放弃了原来很酷的 使用气尖发动机的萤火虫阿尔法小型运载火箭
扯衣服吟唱
It was cool but they ended up completely starting over with a new rocket, still called the Alpha
但他们最终完全以一种新的火箭重新开始 仍然叫做阿尔法
but this is basically an entirely new rocket.
但这基本上是一枚全新的火箭
So fast forward to today and the company has an orbit ready rocket on the launch pad.
那么快进到现在 该公司在发射台上有一枚准备好的轨道火箭
And may I say, I think this is one of the coolest looking rockets I've ever seen.
而我可以说 这是我见过的最酷的火箭之一
I love that paint job.
我喜欢这个涂装
Just like the Electronic, Alpha is made entirely from carbon composite tanks.
就像电子一样 阿尔法火箭箭体完全使用碳纤维复合材料
But Alpha is a much larger rocket.
但阿尔法是一枚大得多的火箭
In fact, Alpha is the largest carbon composite rocket that will fly to date.
事实上 阿尔法是迄今为止将飞行的最大的碳纤维复合材料火箭
Again, like every other rocket here so far Alpha runs on Kerolox.
同样 就像我们前面正片中谈过的火箭一样 阿尔法使用液氧煤油推进剂
But its engines are doing something very unique.
但它的发动机做了一些非常独特的事情
They run on the tap-off cycle,
其使用抽气循环
which is where you basically just punch a hole in the side of your combustion chamber
基本上就是在燃烧室的一侧打一个洞
and then have that high pressure gas spin the turbine to turn your pumps.
然后让燃烧室中的高压气体来旋转涡轮泵
蓝色起源：感觉有被冒犯到
It's a cycle type that has never flown on an orbital rocket
这是一种从未在轨道级火箭上飞行过的循环类型
and Firefly will be using them on both stages.
而萤火虫将在两个分级上都使用它们
There's four Reaver engines on the first stage and a single Lightning engine on the upper stage.
第一级有四台金甲虫发动机 而上面级使用一台闪电发动机
Firefly is based out of Austin, Texas, which is where their headquarters are,
萤火虫公司总部位于德克萨斯州奥斯汀市
but they actually build and test their hardware about 80 kilometers Northwest of Austin.
但实际上是在奥斯汀西北约80公里处建造并测试其设备
They'll be launching Alpha from SLC 2W in Vandenberg Space Force Base in California
他们将从加利福尼亚州范登堡太空军基地的SLC-2W发射阿尔法
where their first Alpha is on the pad as of the making of this video, just waiting to fly.
在制作这段视频时 他们的第一枚阿尔法就在发射台上 正等待飞行
[bright upbeat music]
[明亮欢快的音乐]
Next up, we have ABL Space systems with their RS-1 Rocket.
接下来 是ABL空间系统的RS-1火箭
ABL is focusing on trying to make the most simple and cost effective rocket ever made.
ABL专注于尝试制造有史以来最简单和最划算的火箭
Like the others, it also runs on Kerolox.
与其他火箭一样 它也使用液氧煤油推进剂
And like most of the other rockets here the engines they're using are 3D printed.
和正片里的大多数其他火箭一样 其使用的发动机是3D打印的
Launcher：感觉有被冒犯到
Their E2 engines are open cycle.
他们的E2发动机是开式循环的
There's that familiar nine engines on the first stage
在其一级上有熟悉的九台发动机
and a single vacuum optimized E2 engine on the second stage.
而其二级有一台真空优化E2发动机
I think one of the standout features of ABL kind of similar to Astra is
我认为ABL与阿斯特拉类似的一个突出特点是
that they can launch really from anywhere.
他们真的可以从任何地方发射
ABL just packs up their entire launch infrastructure in standard shipping containers.
ABL只是将他们的整个发射基础设施打包在标准的运输集装箱中
And when I say everything, I mean, absolutely everything.
当我说一切时 我的意思是 绝对的一切
They're integrated mobile launch system is called GS0
他们的综合移动发射系统被称为GS0
which stands for something, something, something we couldn't actually find it quoted anywhere
它到底代表着什么 实际上无法在任何地方找到它的引文
but I would assume it's probably something like Ground System Zero.
但我认为它可能是指零号地面系统 之类的东西
Maybe it's my love of tiny homes and shipping container houses
也许是我对小房子和集装箱房屋的热爱
that makes me love these shipping container concepts.
这让我喜欢这些集装箱概念
It's cool to think you could just ship the systems anywhere with a concrete pad
想到你可以把这些系统运到任何有混凝土地面的地方 这很酷
and have a launch pad in your own backyard if you want it to.
如果你想的话 可以在你自己的后院拥有一个发射台
But what's important for commercial and government customers is
但对商业和政府客户来说 最重要的是
they can operate from all FAA licensed sites.
他们可以在所有美国联邦航空管理局许可的地点进行操作
So all of the sites we're familiar with in the United States
因此 这包括所有我们所熟悉的美国发射场
应该是指卡姆登太空港
and even including one in Camden county, Georgia.
甚至包括在乔治亚州卡姆登县的一个发射场
Like so many of the other companies in this group,
就像我前面说的很多公司一样
ABL is based out of California, specifically El Segundo which is right next to Hawthorne.
ABL的总部设在加州 具体来说是埃尔塞贡多 就在霍桑旁边
相对论 /// 地球人-1
[bright upbeat music]
[明亮欢快的音乐]
A lot of the rockets we're talking about today are using 3D printing for a lot of parts and even engines.
我们今天讨论的很多火箭都在使用3D打印技术制造很多部件 甚至是发动机
But none are taking 3D printing quite as far as Relativity.
但没有一枚火箭能像相对论那样将3D打印技术发挥到极致
Relativity is literally trying to 3D print the entire rocket.
相对论正在尝试3D打印整个火箭
Yeah, like all of it.
是的 就是整个都用3D打印
That's right.
没错
Their Terran-1 rocket is pretty much entirely 3D printed.
他们的地球人-1火箭几乎是完全3D打印的
The fuselage and all.
箭体以及其他部件
They're trying to reduce the number of parts by 100 times.
他们正试图将零件的数量减少到原先的1%
This greatly simplifies manufacturing, reduces part lead time,
这大大简化了制造 减少了零件的交货时间(前置时间)
simplifies the supply chain and theoretically increases reliability.
简化了供应链 并在理论上提高了可靠性
And just look at how big their 3D printer called Stargate is.
同时 就看看他们的3D打印机 星门有多大
It's actually one of the world's largest 3D printers ever made.
实际上 它是有史以来世界上最大的3D打印机之一
This allows Relativity to make unique shapes and designs
这使得相对论能够进行独特的设计 做出独特的形状
but it also allows them to quickly make changes to their designs
但也允许其快速地对设计进行修改
since they don't have to really change any tooling.
因为在修改设计时不需要修改任何工具(模具)
The first stage of the Terran-1 has 9 Aeon 1 engines
地球人-1的一级有9台宙1发动机
and the upper stage has a single vacuum optimized Aeon engine.
而上面级有一台真空优化的宙发动机
Aeons are open cycle and run on liquid natural gas and liquid oxygen.
宙发动机是开式循环的 推进剂使用液态天然气和液氧
A fun note about this rocket is
关于这枚火箭的一个有趣的事情是
they're planning to use autogenous pressurization to backfill the tanks
他们计划使用自生压力来加压储罐
much like the Space Shuttle's external fuel tank or Starship
很像航天飞机的外部燃料储罐 或者星船
但是实际上航天飞机的RS-25还是使用到了氦气用来密封管路，
虽然密封发动机的氦气要比加压储罐的少
which removes the need for expensive and hard to manage helium in the system.
这样就不需要在系统中使用昂贵且难以管理的氦气
Relativity is based out of Long Beach and Los Angeles, California
相对论公司总部设在加利福尼亚州长滩和洛杉矶
where their headquarters and factories are located.
同时 工厂与总部处在同一位置
But they'll be launching the Terran-1 from LC-16 at Cape Canaveral Space Force Station,
但他们将从卡纳维拉尔角空军基地的LC-16发射地球人-1
and they also have a site picked out at Vandenberg as well.
同时 他们还在范登堡(太空军基地)选择了一个发射场
Okay, so that's our list of current and upcoming small lift launchers.
好了 这就是我们列出的 目前即将发射的小型运载火箭的清单
How do they compare against each other
(那么) 它们之间的对比如何
and are any of them making improvements
以及 相比于十多年前SpaceX的猎鹰1号取得的成果
over what SpaceX accomplished over 10 years ago with their Falcon 1?
它们的改进有多少
对比
[bright upbeat music]
[明亮欢快的音乐]
Okay my friends, it's time we line these babies up side by side.
好了 我的朋友们 现在是时候把这些宝贝并排放在一起了
So let's do just that.
那么 这样做
So we can get a sense of how big each rocket really is.
才能让我们感觉到每枚火箭到底有多大
For being small lift launchers, some of these rockets are getting pretty big.
作为小型运载火箭 这些火箭中的一些已经变得相当大
Terran-1 for example is actually about half the height of SpaceX's Falcon 9.
例如 地球人-1实际上大约是SpaceX的猎鹰9号高度的一半
Next up their width.
接下来是它们的宽度
Again, Alpha and Terran-1 are pretty big rockets.
同样 阿尔法和地球人-1是相当大的火箭
Much bigger than I think most people might realize.
比我认为大多数人可能意识到的要大得多
But the one thing that's kind of surprising here is LauncherOne.
但这里有一点令人惊讶的是发射器一号
It's probably because when you see a picture of it attached to a massive 747,
可能是因为当你看到那幅画面 也就是它固定在那架巨大的747上时
it looks like a little rinky dinky missile or something
它看起来像是一枚小巧精致的导弹或者之类的东西
but then when you see people next to it you realize it's indeed a surprisingly big rocket.
但当你看到它旁边的人时 你才会发现它确实是一枚令人惊讶的大火箭
Okay now let's show each rockets thrust, the cycle type, and specific impulse of the first two stages
好了 现在让我们展示一下每枚火箭的推力 循环类型和前两级的比冲
and whether or not they have a kick stage.
以及它们是否还具有额外的末级/三级
起飞质量数据来自www.spacelaunchreport.com，
运力，价格均取每日宇航员提供的500km SSO的数据
起飞质量
约10t
运载系数
约3.35%
起飞质量
约12.55t
运载系数
约1.59%
起飞质量
约25.8t
运载系数
约1.16%
起飞质量
约32.3t
运载系数
约1.39%
Maybe more important than their sizes and payload fairing volume is
也许比尺寸和有效载荷整流罩体积更重要的是
how much can these vehicles actually put into orbit?
这些飞行器究竟能把多重的东西送入轨道？
For these numbers we're going to look at
对于这些数字 我们要看的是
how much they can lift to Sun-Synchronous Orbit or SSO
它们能将多少东西送入太阳同步轨道或者说SSO
能看出谁数据离谱吧
which is a number we could get an accurate quote on from each company.
这是一个我们可以从每个公司获得准确引用的数字
This is similar to a polar orbit
太阳同步轨道类似于极地轨道
and takes more energy to get into than just a low inclination orbit.
相比低倾角的轨道 需要更多的能量来进入
Astra's Rocket, although tiny, it's a very capable small lift launcher.
阿斯特拉的火箭 虽然很小 但它是一个运力相当不错的小运载火箭
But the other outlier here is the RS-1.
但这里的另一个异类是RS-1
It's the payload leader, but it's not even the biggest rocket.
它的运力最大 但它甚至还不是(尺寸)最大的火箭
单位运力
价格$/kg
单位运力价格$/kg 13333
单位运力
价格$/kg
So now the price.
那么现在来谈谈价格
And again, we should take some of these numbers with a little grain of salt
再说一遍 我们应该对其中的一些数字持谨慎态度
because some of these are just rough quotes that companies have published.
因为其中一些只是公司公布的粗略报价
But in general, this seems to be about the lowest cost for most of these companies
但总的来说 这似乎是大多数这些公司提供的最低费用
or maybe even like a starting point for a dedicated ride.
或者甚至可能是特定发射的起步价
So don't actually put too much weight on these numbers.
所以实际上不要把这些数字看得太重
And also the Falcon 1 is adjusted for today's dollar.
同样 猎鹰1号也是根据今天的美元调整的
As far as just a base price,
至于这样的一个基本价格
if you totally had to book a ride all on your own and have a satellite under 500 kilograms,
如果是为一颗500千克以下质量的卫星(接近335千克)预订一次发射
it'd be hard to be Astra's price.
那就很难做到阿斯特拉的价格了
But then again, we don't actually know what it cost for the full 500 kilograms.
但话又说回来 我们实际上不知道整整500千克载荷发射的价格
At 2.5 million is likely just a starting point for a much lighter payload.
250万美元很可能只是一个更轻的有效载荷的起点(如拼车发射)
But one for sure, you cannot discount Rocket Lab's orbital launch experience.
但有一点可以肯定 你不能忽视火箭实验室的轨道发射经验
This is a very serious consideration
这是一个非常严肃的考虑(所以其价格更为真实)
because flying regularly to orbit is vastly different from some just vague target initial launch.
因为定期飞往轨道与一些只是模糊的初始发射(费用)目标有很大的不同
And this is even despite Rocket Lab's recent setback.
而这哪怕算上火箭实验室最近的发射失败也是一样的
For now they're the only ones regularly flying and with a lot of experience under their belt.
就目前而言 其是唯一定期飞行 同时有着大量经验的公司
没事，前面字幕里已经标过单位千克价格了
Now might be tempting to do a dollar to kilogram ratio here for these rockets.
现在可能很想给这些火箭放出单位千克价格的数据
But unfortunately with only knowing the starting point and the maximum payload potential,
但不幸的是 在只知道起点价格和最大有效载荷潜力的情况下
it just might not be a fair or accurate comparison.
这种比较可能并不公平或准确
But here's the reminder,
但要注意的是
small lift launchers don't always look great for their dollar to kilogram ratio
小运载火箭单位千克运力的价格费用并不是很好(低)
because you're buying a dedicated ride to space.
因为你买的是通往太空的专用(专车)发射
If your satellite is say 300 kilograms
如果你的卫星是300千克的
you would want to purchase the cheapest rocket that can support that period.
你只会想购买能运载这一卫星的最便宜的火箭
So most of the time that dollar to kilogram ratio number is
因此 大多数时候 单位千克运力的价格
a lot less important than the final amount at the end of the day to launch your satellite.
会比最后发射卫星的价格(总价)的重要性要低得多
How much are you writing that check for?
也就是那张(用来发射的)支票到底是多少钱？
But as far as how do these compare to the Falcon 1?
但至于这些火箭与猎鹰1号的比较如何呢？
Well, some are potentially making some improvements
好吧 有些火箭确实是有所改进的
but honestly, others still can't quite keep up with what SpaceX was doing 12 years ago.
但说实话 其他的仍然不能完全跟上SpaceX在12年前的表现
It's honestly pretty spectacular what SpaceX accomplished in the early days.
说实话 早期SpaceX的成就是非常好的
Had they kept flying Falcon 1?
如果当时他们继续飞行猎鹰1号呢？
I have no doubt they would have continued making tweaks and performance and price,
我相信他们会继续对性能和价格进行调整
and it would have been even more competitive by now.
如果坚持到现在 甚至会(比这里的数据)更有竞争力
Wow, they were honestly super far ahead of the game.
哇 他们在这个行业中真的超级领先
So that's all these rockets compare side by side.
所以这就是所有这些火箭的并列比较
So let's get some final thoughts in.
那么 让我们总结下吧
总结
[bright upbeat music]
[明亮欢快的音乐]
Clearly, there's a flood of small sat launchers coming online
很明显 有大量的小卫星运载火箭即将发射
and competing for a healthy handful of small satellites and cube sats.
并且将争夺大量的小卫星和立方星发射订单
But the ultimate question for me is how many of these companies can co-exist.
但对我来说 最终的问题是这些公司中有多少能够共存(生存下来)
In my outside opinion,
我作为一个局外人的观点是
it feels like there's really only room for about four or maybe five of them to exist
只有四到五个公司有存在的空间
based on the current demand of payloads.
基于目前对有效载荷的需求
And at some point, it'll almost be too late to join in a small sat launching game
而且 加入小卫星发射行业时机很重要 不能太晚
unless you have some big radical breakthrough that makes you super ultra competitive somehow.
除非一些大的根本性的突破使你有超强的竞争力
At the end of the day, one thing we need to keep in mind is there are definitely advantages to going bigger.
最后 我们需要记住的一件事是 做大肯定有好处
There's a lot of launch operation costs that are just simply fixed costs
有很多发射操作成本只是简单的固定成本
like range and safety personnel time
比如说发射区域安全控制的人员时间
and a few things that don't increase linearly with the size of the vehicle.
还有一些不随航天器尺寸增加而线性增长的东西
As in launching a Falcon 9 that could launch say 50 times that of a small sat launcher,
就像发射一枚猎鹰9号 其发射质量是一枚小卫星火箭的50倍
likely doesn't require 50 times the amount of people to operate it.
但可能并不需要50倍的人力去操作它
So there's always some benefits to just simply being larger that small lift launchers can't overcome.
因此 单纯的大型化总有一些小火箭所不能获得的好处
But the fact that you could book a ride for your small satellite
但是 事实是 你可以为小卫星专门预订一次发射
and be flying potentially much quicker directly to your desired orbit is extremely appealing.
并有可能更快地直接飞到你所期望的轨道上 是非常有吸引力的
I know for those of us who are outside of the industry,
我知道对于我们这些行外人来说
it can be kind of hard to understand why that's really that important.
可能有点难以理解为什么这真的那么重要
But for those trying to be first to market with a new satellite or a new concept
但是对于那些试图将新卫星或新概念率先推向市场的人来说
getting a ride to prove out your technology in a hurry is actually a huge, huge deal.
将载荷快速发射 并验证你的技术 实际上是很重要的
But as far as which of these companies do I think will be around in 10 years,
但是 至于前面说的这些公司中 哪些会在10年内生存下来
I wanna think all of them may be but that's maybe a little bit unrealistic.
我当然想所有的公司都能生存下来 但这可能有点不现实
In fact, until a company is flying and flying regularly,
事实上 在一家公司开始定期发射之前
there's just so much risk involved in developing and launching.
其在开发和发射方面都面临太多的风险
But I think Rocket Lab has proven to be a solid player with plenty of demand
但我认为火箭实验室已被证明是一个有着大量需求的 坚实的市场参与者
and clearly a system set up for rapid launch cadence.
而且显然构筑了一个能快速发射的系统
I fully expect there'll be around longterm
我完全期待他们会长期存在下去
and I'm excited for them to get into the medium lift launchers with their neutron rocket.
而我也很高兴他们能通过中子火箭进入中型运载火箭的领域
Personally, I'm very excited about Terran-1 being 3D printed
就个人而言 我对地球人-1的3D打印感到非常兴奋
but that also seems like a fairly risky endeavor
但这似乎也是一个相当有风险的尝试
since it's utilizing 3D printing at a new never before done scale.
因为它是在一个新的前所未有的规模上使用3D打印技术
But if they can pull it off, it might be a pretty massive disruptor.
但如果能攻克这一难题 可能会成为一个相当大的搅局者
I really like LauncherOne because I think air launching is cool
我非常喜欢发射器一号 因为我认为空中发射很酷
but of course that's not reason enough.
但这样的理由并不充分
I also think there's some payloads that will almost require LauncherOne
我还认为会有一些有效载荷几乎必须借助发射器一号来发射
including payloads that they'll want to integrate on site
比如有的载荷可能需要在发射场进行整合(快速响应)
or not ship it across the world first before they integrate it onto the rocket.
或者在整合到火箭上以后再运输到世界上的其他地方
Well, there's also the option for the LauncherOne
那么 发射器一号也有着这样的发射选项
to fly to another country and launch from there which might be appealing for some payloads.
就是飞到另一个国家并从那里发射 这对某些有效载荷可能更具吸引力
I think Firefly's Alpha is a real solid contender especially if you need more performance
我认为萤火虫的阿尔法是一个强有力的竞争者 特别是在性能方面
and the fact that they have a rocket on the launch pad as we speak,
还有就是现在他们已经有枚火箭放在了发射台上
makes them a step ahead of a few others in this comparison.
使他们在这次比较中比其他几家公司领先了一步
I personally think if you can get your rocket operational this year, you'll be here to stay,
我个人认为 如果你能在今年让你的火箭投入使用 就能在市场中留下
but the race is still on until you're regularly and reliably flying.
但比赛仍在继续 直到你能定期并可靠地飞行
I mean, just look at Astra who has gotten so close to orbit
我是指 只要看看阿斯特拉 其火箭已经非常接近入轨了
or Rocket Lab who is very experienced
以及富有经验的火箭实验室
but just saw an unexpected failure on their 20th mission.
然而在第20次任务中却出现了意外的失败
Spaceflight is hard.
航天是困难的
It really is.
它确实是
It takes a lot of perfection to do regularly.
只有精益求精才能定期(成功)发射
And these small sat launchers are often riding on a very, very thin margin for what's even physically possible.
而这些小卫星火箭往往是贴着物理法则 只有一点点余量可供发射
But something about that just makes them even cooler to me.
但这一点让我觉得它们更酷了
Small lift launch vehicles, tiny, but awesome.
小型运载火箭 小而精
I hope the best for all of these companies
我希望所有这些公司都能做到最好
and any other aspiring company working on getting their first rocket to the pad.
以及任何其他有志于发射的公司
I feel like you need to be extra creative and extra plucky to make a small lift launcher work.
我觉得你需要有特别的创造力和胆量 才能使小火箭成功发射
So cheers to all of you trying.
那么 为你们所有人的努力而欢呼吧
So what do you think?
那么你怎么看？
Do you think any of these launchers stand out?
Are there any that you're really excited about in particular?
Which ones do you think will still be here in 10 years?
I mean, of course I hope all of them are but maybe the biggest question,
do you think small sat launches are here to stay
or do you think bigger ride share options will ultimately just win out?
Let me know your thoughts in the comments below.
Thanks to Casper Stanley for the awesome 3D rocket renders as always his work is amazing.
Find him on Twitter, find his YouTube channel and find his Rocket Explorer app on the Steam Store.
And we also need to thank the sponsor of this video, KiwiCo.
KiwiCo makes amazing hands-on projects and toys designed to expose kids to concepts in Steam.
So science technology, engineering, art and math.
Personally, I wish KiwiCO was around when I was a kid because I was always building things,
constantly tinkering and playing with things around the house
but I almost never had the right materials to finish my little projects or ideas,
and I was always making a mess or losing my dad's tools.
Sorry, dad.
KiwiCo is a monthly crate sent to your door that comes
with all the supplies needed right in the box to make awesome projects.
Not only that they have eight subscription lines so each catering to different age groups and topics.
They come fully loaded with really clear and kid-friendly instructions
and an educational magazine filled with content to learn even more about the crates theme.
So not only is it fun, it's also engaging and educational.
So win, win, win.
Now, I'm not gonna lie.
I saw this robotic arm online and I just had to play with it.
When I was growing up I wanted to be a...
Well, first I wanted to be a tractor which is not really something you can be when you grow up.
And then I wanted to be a scorpion trainer which may have been a good career,
but for a long time actually for most of my childhood,
I wanted to be a prosthetic and robotic engineer.
So this is definitely like hitting the fields for me.
This is really cool and I'm really glad that I got a chance to play with this.
You can get 50% off your first month of any crate by going to kiwico.com/everydayastronaut.
There is a link below in the description as well.
So thank you to KiwiCo for sponsoring this video.
I owe a huge thank you to my Patreon Supporters
for helping make content like this and everything else that we do here at every astronaut possible.
If you want to get exclusive access to behind the scenes streams,
or our amazing discord channel and community,
or even just get your thoughts and comments on scripts and videos before they come out,
head on over to patrion.com/everydayastronaut.
Thank you.
And while you're online,
be sure and check out our awesome web store for shirts like this the Aerospike shirt,
which is not only one of my favorite engines, it's also one of my favorite shirts.
But browse around there was lots of really cool stuff.
And we finally got our full flow stage combustion cycle hoodies back in stock.
So there's tons of cool stuff.
And just shop around,
maybe grab something for yourself or a friend and show your support
for the channel by going to everydayastronaut.com/shop.
Thanks everybody. That's going to do it for me.
谢谢大家观看 本期节目到这里就结束了
I'm Tim Dodd, the everyday astronaut,
我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
bringing space down to Earth, for everyday people.
将太空的知识带给地球上的普通人
[gentle music]
[轻柔的音乐]